<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Academic | My Site</title><link>https://www.kleinloog.ch/tag/academic/</link><atom:link href="https://www.kleinloog.ch/tag/academic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Academic</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Dedicated to the public domain · [Unlicensed](https://github.com/akleinloog/akleinloog.github.io/blob/master/LICENSE)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.kleinloog.ch/images/icon_hu1d96926d990b8c2ce1741b9516caf288_71361_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Academic</title><link>https://www.kleinloog.ch/tag/academic/</link></image><item><title>Setting up this Blog - Part 2</title><link>https://www.kleinloog.ch/post/my-blog-pt2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.kleinloog.ch/post/my-blog-pt2/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the second part in a series of posts detailing the set up of my personal blog.
It details how to enable google analytics, commenting and a simple contact page.
See &lt;a href="https://www.kleinloog.ch/post/my-blog-pt1">part 1&lt;/a> for the basic setup.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="enable-google-analytics">Enable Google Analytics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://marketingplatform.google.com/about/analytics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Analytics&lt;/a> can provide you with some interesting insights on your site&amp;rsquo;s visitors and the way they use your site. Enabling it on my personal blog provides a nice opportunity to learn a bit more about the possibilities it offers to site owners.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lucky for me, it is a straight forward exercise. After signing up for google analytics and creating an account for your website, all you need to do is open your &lt;em>params.toml&lt;/em> in _/config/&lt;em>default&lt;/em> and add the account id:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-toml">############################
## Marketing
############################
[marketing]
google_analytics = &amp;quot;UA-***&amp;quot;
# google_tag_manager = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>I signed up for &lt;a href="https://marketingplatform.google.com/about/tag-manager/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Tag Manager&lt;/a> as well, and tried to activate it, but no luck so far. In order to get Google Analytics to work I had to comment out the &lt;em>google_tag_manager&lt;/em> entry. If I decide to take another look at this and get it to work, I&amp;rsquo;ll detail it in a follow up post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The next step is to configure the base URL of your site, in &lt;em>config.toml&lt;/em> in _/config/&lt;em>default&lt;/em>. If you used a custom domain:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-toml"># The URL of your site.
baseurl = &amp;quot;https://www.yourdomain.com/&amp;quot;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Otherwise, use your GitHub Pages URL:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-toml"># The URL of your site.
baseurl = &amp;quot;https://&amp;lt;username here&amp;gt;.github.io/&amp;quot;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The last change is an improvement to the deploy script we created in the previous post.
In &lt;em>deploy.sh&lt;/em> replace the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">echo &amp;quot;Running Hugo Build&amp;quot;
hugo -t academic
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>with:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">echo &amp;quot;Running Hugo Build&amp;quot;
env HUGO_ENV=&amp;quot;production&amp;quot; hugo --gc --minify -t academic -b https://&amp;lt;username here&amp;gt;.github.io
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Doing so will activate the Google Analytics scripts when the site is running in production. In addition, it also &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/commands/hugo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">instructs Hugo&lt;/a> to run some cleanup tasks after the build and to minify the output, something I didn&amp;rsquo;t pay attention to in my previous post.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="enable-google-search-console">Enable Google Search Console&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Another thing I decided to add is &lt;a href="https://search.google.com/search-console/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Search Console&lt;/a>, another free-to-use service offered by Google that helps you monitor, maintain, and troubleshoot your site&amp;rsquo;s presence in Google Search results.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After using the &amp;lsquo;URL prefix&amp;rsquo; method, my site ownership was automatically verified based on the Google Analytics account. I added an additional verification method by going to &lt;em>Settings-&amp;gt;Ownership Verification&lt;/em>, and selecting &lt;em>HTML File&lt;/em>. Download the file, add it to your &lt;em>/static&lt;/em> folder and redeploy the site:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">./deploy.sh
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Of course I realize that, as is the case with most &amp;lsquo;free service&amp;rsquo; offerings, I am being part of the product here. Google will use all information they get in ways they see fit. Since what I am doing here is &amp;lsquo;out in the open&amp;rsquo; and dedicated to the public domain, I figured it would make a good opportunity to learn more about these Google services, and I appreciate that the collected information (or at least some of it) is shared with me as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="commenting-with-disqus">Commenting with Disqus&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Enabling others to comment on your site turns it into an interactive site and is relatively easy to do.
First go to &lt;a href="https://disqus.com">https://disqus.com&lt;/a> and sign up. I selected the basic, free package. Then open &lt;em>params.toml&lt;/em> in your _config/&lt;em>default&lt;/em> directory and fill in the comments section to enable commenting:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-toml">############################
## Comments
############################
[comments]
...
engine = 1
...
[comments.disqus]
shortname = &amp;quot;&amp;lt;shortname&amp;gt;&amp;quot; # Paste the shortname from your Disqus dashboard
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>When you run the site locally, the commenting section won&amp;rsquo;t be enabled, but you should see a warning like
&lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Disqus comments not available by default when the website is previewed locally.&amp;quot;&lt;/em> at the bottom of your posts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Deploy your website to production and see how it works!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="contact-page">Contact Page&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Adding a simple contact page can be done with Academic&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/page-builder/#contact" target="_blank" rel="noopener">contact widget&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this side, I decided to add it to the bottom of the about page, and in addition, add a top-level menu and a link from my profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To add a top level menu, open _config/&lt;em>default/menus.toml&lt;/em> and add:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-toml">[[main]]
name = &amp;quot;Contact&amp;quot;
url = &amp;quot;about/#contact&amp;quot;
weight = 50
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>In _config/&lt;em>default/params.toml&lt;/em>, make sure that an email address is configured.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To add a link from your profile, open _authors/admin/&lt;em>index.md&lt;/em> and add this to the social section:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-toml">- icon: envelope
icon_pack: fas
link: 'about/#contact'
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>To add the contact form itself, in the &lt;em>content/about/&lt;/em> folder, add contact.md with the following content:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-toml">+++
# Contact widget.
widget = &amp;quot;contact&amp;quot;
headless = true
active = true
weight = 50
title = &amp;quot;Contact&amp;quot;
subtitle = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;
# Automatically link email and phone?
autolink = true
# Email form provider
# 0: Disable email form
# 1: Netlify (requires that the site is hosted by Netlify)
# 2: formspree.io
email_form = 2
+++
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>This sets up your site to use &lt;a href="https://formspree.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Formspree&lt;/a> to email you the request.
After deploying to production, simply fill in the form once and you will receive an email to complete your registration.
Their free plan gives you a limited amount of monthly submissions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The contact widget can be further customized by providing additional information in your &lt;em>params.toml&lt;/em>, see the &lt;a href="https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/page-builder/#contact" target="_blank" rel="noopener">docs&lt;/a> for more detail.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Setting up this Blog - Part 1</title><link>https://www.kleinloog.ch/post/my-blog-pt1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.kleinloog.ch/post/my-blog-pt1/</guid><description>&lt;p>Welcome to the first in a series of posts that detail how I set up of this blog. It covers the basic steps needed to get started.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I use &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hugo&lt;/a> as a static site generator and &lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Visual Studio Code&lt;/a> as editor. The resulting website is hosted using &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub Pages&lt;/a>. A nice combination of open source tools with a free hosting provider that poses no restrictions in terms of traffic, size, etc.
Sounds like a perfect match to me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Familiarity with git and the command line are assumed. I use a Mac, some of the commands may need to be translated to your environment.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Following this &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/hosting-and-deployment/hosting-on-github/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hugo tutorial&lt;/a>, I created two repositories on GitHub.
One named &lt;em>website&lt;/em> for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/akleinloog/website" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sources&lt;/a>, and another one for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/akleinloog/akleinloog.github.io" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generated website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The name of the repository for the generated website has to be specific in order for it to be picked up by GitHub Pages.
In my case: &lt;strong>akleinloog.github.io&lt;/strong>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I decided to dedicate both repositories to the public domain and therefore used the &lt;a href="https://choosealicense.com/licenses/unlicense/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UNLICENSE&lt;/a>.
Feel free to use anything you find there as you see fit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The next step is to clone the repository used for the source:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">git clone https://github.com/&amp;lt;username here&amp;gt;/website.git
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>And open the project in Visual Studio Code:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">cd website
code .
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Add the following .gitignore file and optionally, save the code workspace:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r"># MacOS Files
.DS_Store
# Hugo Working Folders
resources/
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Install Hugo if not already installed:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">brew install hugo
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>And initialize your repository for Hugo:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">hugo new site . --force
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h2 id="select-a-theme">Select a theme&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A good overview of available themes can be found &lt;a href="https://jamstackthemes.dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.
Select Hugo and order the themes by Stars gives you an overview of the most used themes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to try &lt;a href="https://sourcethemes.com/academic/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Academic&lt;/a>, a feature rich, open source theme developed by George Cushen and made available under the &lt;a href="https://choosealicense.com/licenses/mit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MIT&lt;/a> license. Thanks George!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the theme as a git submodule:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">git submodule add https://github.com/gcushen/hugo-academic.git themes/academic
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Familiarize yourself with Academic, and &lt;a href="https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/customization/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">customize&lt;/a> it as you see fit.
A good way to do that, is to clone the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sourcethemes/academic-kickstart" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Academic Kickstart&lt;/a> project in a separate directory.
It provides a good demonstration of what the theme has to offer.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="add-some-content">Add some content&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>First add the configuration files. You can copy the ones from the Academic Kickstart project to get started. Read through them and adjust as you see fit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also copy the &lt;em>page_sharer.toml&lt;/em> file in the &lt;em>data&lt;/em> folder to your local project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Playing around with Academic&amp;rsquo;s many widgets using the Kickstart project should give you a fair idea on what other content you want to add.
You can also have a look at my &lt;a href="https://github.com/akleinloog/website" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sources repository&lt;/a> to see what I did for this blog.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="try-it-out-locally">Try it out locally&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Experiment with the configuration options and the structure. Run the site in development mode using:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">hugo server
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The site will be available at &lt;em>http://localhost:1313&lt;/em>.
Whenever you save your changes, Hugo will react and automatically refresh the website, providing a very pleasant live-editing experience.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="get-ready-to-publish">Get ready to publish&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Add the repository for the generated website as a git submodule:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">git submodule add -b master https://github.com/&amp;lt;username here&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;username here&amp;gt;.github.io.git public
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Doing so ensures that the HTML and JavaScript generated by Hugo will be placed in that repository.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, we&amp;rsquo;ll do a manual run. Generate your website:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">hugo -t academic
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Test the generated output using the &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/serve" target="_blank" rel="noopener">serve package&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">cd public
npx serve
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h2 id="automate-it">Automate it&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Add a file called deploy.sh to the sources repository&amp;rsquo;s main folder. Ensure it is executable:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">chmod +x deploy.sh
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Add the following content to that file:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">#!/bin/sh
set -e
echo &amp;quot;Cleaning Publish Folder&amp;quot;
rm -r ./public/*
echo &amp;quot;Running Hugo Build&amp;quot;
hugo -t academic
cd public
echo &amp;quot;Adding changes to git&amp;quot;
git add .
msg=&amp;quot;regenerating site content $(date)&amp;quot;
git commit -m &amp;quot;$msg&amp;quot;
echo &amp;quot;Pushing to master&amp;quot;
git push origin master
cd ..
echo &amp;quot;Deployment Finished&amp;quot;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>This script uses Hugo to generate your website and commit the changes to the generated website repository.
By pushing these changes to GitHub, the script effectively deploys your website to production. Give it a try:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>./deploy.sh
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Navigate to your GitHub Pages URL to see the result!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="add-a-custom-domain-name">Add a custom domain name&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Using a custom domain name for your GitHub pages is relatively straight forward.
First register a domain name and then configure the &lt;a href="https://kb.pressable.com/article/dns-record-types-explained/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DNS settings&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Create the following A records for your domain to point it to GitHub&amp;rsquo;s servers:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>185.199.108.153
185.199.109.153
185.199.110.153
185.199.111.153
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Then add a CNAME record for www that points to the your GitHub site.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then go to the GitHub repository settings of your generated site.
In the GitHub Pages section, enter the domain you&amp;rsquo;ve registered in the custom domain field, with the &lt;strong>www.&lt;/strong> prefix, and save it.
This will trigger a check-in that adds a CNAME file with the domain that you have specified.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Keep in mind that may take some time for DNS changes to take effect, and for the SSL certificates to be generated.
Once completed, check the &amp;lsquo;Enforce HTTPS&amp;rsquo; checkbox and the setup is completed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your domain name will be forwarded to your &lt;strong>www.&lt;/strong> and so will your GitHub pages and HTTPS will be automatically enforces, with valid a certificate for your URL, free of charge!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>See the GitHub Pages docs for &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/managing-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more information&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/troubleshooting-custom-domains-and-github-pages" target="_blank" rel="noopener">troubleshooting tips&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="update-the-source-repository">Update the source repository&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The last thing to do, before making other modifications to your site, is to secure the CNAME file in your source repository so that it does not get deleted when the website is regenerated. First pull the changes:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-bash">cd public
git pull --all
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>This will update the local module and add the CNAME file. Now copy that file from the &lt;em>public&lt;/em> folder to the &lt;em>static&lt;/em> folder so it will be re-added when the site is regenerated. Commit and push your changes and you are good to go!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I hope you may have learned something from this, as I did. In &lt;a href="https://www.kleinloog.ch/post/my-blog-pt2">Part 2&lt;/a> I will add support for Google Analytics, comments and a simple contact page.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>